{"tossups": [{"question": "The accused spy David Redding was hanged in what is now this state. Leaders from what is now this state negotiated with representatives of George Germain but failed to reach terms with Quebec governor Frederick Haldimand. This state celebrates Jonathan Stark's defeat of British forces before Saratoga on Bennington Battle Day. In 1791, this state became the 14th state to enter the Union, ending its Republic. For ten points, name this state for which Bernie Sanders has served as Senator.", "answer": "<b><u>Vermont</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was home to an early ecumenical [[ECK-yoo-MEN-ih-kull]] council which ruled that Gentiles were not required to keep Jewish laws. A religious leader in this city drove out moneylenders and kicked over tables in a temple he calls a \"house of prayer.\" This city is home to the Church of the Holy Sepulcher [[SEH-pull-kuhr]], which claims to be the location of Jesus's tomb. The location of the Last Supper, for ten points, what is this Israelite city where Jesus was crucified?", "answer": "<b><u>Jerusalem</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This man's navy beat the Earl of Torrington and Ralph Delaval at the Battle of Beachy Head, preventing an invasion after his army won at Fleurus [[FLOOR-us]]. This man's attempts to install William von Furstenburg in Cologne [[ko-LOHN]] led to the creation of the League of Augsburg. This man gained Alsace and the Rhine River border with Germany at the Treaty of Ryswick [[RIZ-wik]]. This man revoked the Edict of Nantes and was served by Cardinal Mazarin. For ten points, name this Sun King of France.", "answer": "<b><u>Louis XIV</u></b> (or <b><u>Louis the Great</u></b>; prompt on \"Sun King\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This body's internal structure was studied using the HP3 heat probe aboard the InSight lander in 2018. In 2022, the European/Russian-designed <em>Rosalind Franklin</em> is scheduled to land on this body. In 1877, Giovanni Schiaparelli [[skap-ah-REH-lee]] claimed to be able to see artificial canals on the surface of this body. <em>Opportunity</em> and <em>Curiosity</em> are two of the rovers which have landed on this body. The <em>Perseverance</em> rover searches for signs of ancient life on, for ten points, what fourth planet from the sun?", "answer": "<b><u>Mars</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This action shares roots with the Scandinavian tradition of <em>Holmgang</em>. Andrew Jackson is said to have lost his honor after violating the rules of one of these actions with Charles Dickinson. The shooting version of this action was an exhibition event at the 1906 and 1908 Olympics. Salvador Allende [[ah-YEN-day]] participated in this action with one of his future ambassadors, while Phillip Hamilton died in one of these actions in Weehawken, New Jersey. For ten points, name this honor challenge which occurred between Aaron Burr and Alexander Hamilton.", "answer": "<b><u>Duel</u></b>ing", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An \"Incident\" including the name of this month, perpetrated by the Cherry Blossom Society, attempted to abolish the liberal Taisho democracy in favor of the Showa Restoration. This month names a \u201cCrisis\u201d in which Pierre Trudeau was forced to enact the War Measures Act in Quebec. Alexander Kerensky\u2019s provisional government was overthrown in a \u201cRevolution\u201d named for this month, leading to the Russian Civil War. For ten points, name this autumn month which, in 1917, included the rise of Vladimir Lenin and Soviet Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>October</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "When analyzing this event, Slavoj Zizek [[SLAH-voh ZEE-zek]] applied Marxist and Lacanian analysis in the book <em>Welcome to the Desert of the Real</em>. This event inspired Borradori's [[boh-rah-DOH-rees]] dialogues with Habermas [[HAY-behr-mahs]] and Derrida [[DEH-rih-dah]], published under the title <em>Philosophy in a Time of Terror</em>. For ten points, name this terrorist attack, in which al-Qaeda agents destroyed two skyscrapers in New York.", "answer": "<b><u>9/11</u></b> (or <b><u>September 11</u></b>th; prompt on \"World Trade Center Attacks\" but do not accept answers mentioning bombs)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of one of these events, 231 Koreans were killed by mobs for allegedly causing it. The ruins of the Carmo Convent still stand after being damaged by one of these events in 1755, the first of these events to be scientifically analyzed. An early Chinese device for detecting these events featured dragons that dropped bronze balls into the mouths of toads. San Francisco's Chinatown was destroyed by one of these events in 1906 which also sparked devastating fires. For ten points, name these natural disasters in which the earth's surface shifts.", "answer": "<b><u>Earthquake</u></b>s (accept 1923 Great Kanto <b><u>earthquake</u></b>; accept 1755 Great Lisbon <b><u>earthquake</u></b>; accept 1906 San Francisco <b><u>earthquake</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this state, coordination between the Black farmers of Phillips County in the summer of 1919 led to white posses committing the Elaine Massacre. A governor of this state pressured David Hale into giving a 300 thousand dollar loan to family friend Jim McDougal in order to develop vacation homes in Whitewater. In 1957, Dwight D. Eisenhower force-integrated a high school in this state\u2019s capital against the wishes of Governor Orval Faubus. For ten points, name this southern state with the cities of Hot Springs and Little Rock.", "answer": "<b><u>Arkansas</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's wife commissioned the Godescalc [[GOH-deh-skahlk]] Evangelistary and brought the relics of Saints Gordianus and Epimachus [[EP-ih-MAH-kus]] to Kempten. Poets of the Veronese [[veh-roh-NEH-seh]] school praised the victory of this man's son Carloman over the Avars. Another of this man's sons named Louis blinded Bernard of Italy and issued the <em>Ordinatio Imperii</em> [[or-dih-NAH-tee-oh im-PEH-rih-ee]]. For ten points, name this Frankish Holy Roman Emperor, the grandson of the first Carolingian.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> (or <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; prompt on \u201cCharles I\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "James Moore's expedition in this state led to the Battle of Ayubale [[ai-YOO-bah-leh]]. Luis de C\u00e1ncer [[KAHN-sehr]] was martyred in this state when his mission from King Charles V led him into Tocobaga territory. After a war in the 1830s, about four thousand Seminoles and Black Seminoles were brought to Oklahoma from this state. In the 16th century, Trist\u00e1n de Luna y Arellano [[ar-eh-YAHN-oh]] founded the Spanish colony of Ochuse [[oh-CHOO-say]] in this state's modern city of Pensacola. For ten points, name this southern U.S. state whose capital is Tallahassee.", "answer": "<b><u>Florida</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In one of these institutions, Frank \u201cBig Black\u201d Smith and Cleveland \u201cJomo\u201d Davis led a notable 1971 uprising. The history of these facilities as an extension of slavery and segregation was chronicled by Michelle Alexander in <em>The New Jim Crow</em>. The number of these facilities grew in England due to unpopularity of the \"Bloody Code,\" under which individuals such as petty thieves could be given the death penalty. For ten points, name these facilities, whose overuse is referred to as \"mass incarceration.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Prison</u></b>s (accept <b><u>jail</u></b>s; accept <b><u>penitentiary</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was called the \"patient in a cast\" during the Aprillian government. The slogan \"<em>Allag</em>,\" or \"Change,\" was used by this country's PASOK party, which was brought down by the 1989 Koskotas [[kohs-KOH-tahs]] financial scandal. Students in this country cried \"Bread-Education-Liberty!\" during a 1973 strike targeting its Regime of the Colonels whose reign coincided with that of Constantine II. For ten points, name this country on the Aegean Sea, the site of the Athens Polytechnic uprising.", "answer": "<b><u>Greece</u></b> (or <b><u>Hellenic</u></b> Republic; or <b><u>Hellas</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During a crisis in this state, one mayor said that he was sick of \"lazy\" residents expecting a government \"handout.\" This state's governor falsely claimed that a power shortage in this state was due to renewable energy sources. In February 2021, four million residents of this state lost power due to Winter Storm Uri [[YOOR-ee]]. This state is the only one of the lower 48 states to have its own power grid. For ten points, name this state from which John Cornyn and Ted Cruz have served as U.S. senators.", "answer": "<b><u>Texas</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "During a battle for this city, P.O.W.s like the \u201cAngels of Bataan\u201d were rescued from the Santo Tomas internment camp. The first permanent Trans-Pacific trade route connected the port of Acapulco to this city and was used by the Spanish to exchange luxury goods and spices for New World silver. This city\u2019s Epifanio de los Santos Avenue served as the hub of the People Power Revolution. For ten points, a battle in what capital city's bay led to the U.S. occupation of the Philippines?", "answer": "<b><u>Manila</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In February 2021, this country's militarily-controlled Myawaddy TV falsely claimed that this country's <em>de jure</em> leader was released from custody. A 2021 coup d'\u00e9tat in this country resulted in Tatmadaw [[TAH-MUH-DOH]] leader Min Aung Hlaing [[MIN AHN LANG]] taking <em>de facto</em> power. This country's military was accused of carrying out an ethnic cleansing in Rakhine State of the Rohingya people. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country where State Counsellor Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] was deposed.", "answer": "<b><u>Myanmar</u></b> (accept <b><u>Burma</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The Ortoiroid [[or-TOY-roid]] people traveled to this island from Trinidad and Tobago. This island contained a similar culture to the Salidoid [[SAL-eh-doid]] culture called Hacienda Grande. Diego Salcedo was drowned on this island, which some believed took \"godliness\" from the Spaniards. This island, which locals called <em>Boriken</em>, was led by the <em>cacique</em> [[kah-SEE-keh]] Ag\u00fceyban\u00e1 [[AH-gway-bah-NAH]], whose successor fought Ponce de Le\u00f3n in the 1511 Taino Rebellion. For ten points, name this U.S. commonwealth in the Caribbean.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b> (prompt on \"PR\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Mary Lucy Williams was nearly killed during a 1956 attack on this man's</u></b> <b><u>house. Two years later, Izola Curry nearly killed this man with a letter opener while</u></b> <b><u>he was signing copies of his book (*)</u> </b><em><b>Strive Toward Freedom</b></em><b>. In a speech delivered at the Mason Temple, this man said, \"The issue is the refusal of Memphis to be fair and honest in its dealings with its public servants, who happen to be (*) </b>sanitation workers.\" The next day, this man was shot at the Lorraine Motel. For ten points, name this Civil Rights activist who was assassinated in 1968.", "answer": "Martin Luther <b><u>King</u></b>, Jr. (accept <b><u>MLK</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One thinker from this country inspired a series of communes in the United</u></b> <b><u>States including Utopia, Ohio and Lake Zurich, Illinois. That thinker from this country</u></b> <b><u>proposed societies of 1,620 people, one male and one female from 810 personality</u></b> <b><u>types. In addition to that developer of the (*)</u> \"phalanx\" system, this country was home to a philosopher who used the method of historical genealogy in books such as </b><em><b>Madness and Civilization</b></em><b> and (*) </b><em>The Birth of the Clinic</em>. For ten points, name this home country of Charles Fourier [[SHARL foo-RYEH]] and Michel Foucault [[mee-SHEL foo-KOH]].", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b> (accept <b><u>French</u></b> Republic; accept R\u00e9publique <b><u>Fran\u00e7aise</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>France</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>During a siege of this city, a two-month election was further worsened by the</u></b> <b><u>fact that guards urinated on voters from the Septizodium [[SEPT-ih-ZOH-dee-um]]</u></b> <b><u>roof. A tribune of this city, Cola di Rienzo, fought Stefano Colonna and was arrested by</u></b> <b><u>Charles IV. The (+)</u> Frangipani [[FRAHN-jee-PAH-nee]] and Pierleoni [[PEER-leh-OH-nee]] families feuded in this city in which Petrarch was crowned Poet Laureate. In 1279, (*) </b>Nicholas III moved the Papal seat from the Lateran Palace back to, for ten points, what Italian city's Vatican?", "answer": "<b><u>Rome</u></b> (or <b><u>Roma</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This composer was the alleged author of the posthumously published memoir</u></b> <em><b><u>Testimony</u></b></em><b><u>. This composer's ballet</u> </b><em><b><u>The Limpid Stream</u></b></em><b><u> was denounced by Platon</u></b> <b><u>Kerzhentsev [[plah-TOHN kehr-ZHEN-tsef]] for its depiction of peasant farmers. This</u></b> <b><u>composer was attacked for (*)</u> formalism in the </b><em><b>Pravda</b></em><b> article \"Muddle Instead of Music.\" This composer's seventh symphony debuted during a Nazi (*) </b>siege of its namesake city. For ten points, name this frequent target of Joseph Stalin, the Soviet composer of the <em>Leningrad</em> Symphony.", "answer": "Dmitri <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's Avellanada [[ah-veh-yah-NAH-dah]] laws allowed for European</u></b> <b><u>farmers to gain land. One leader of this country, Justo Jose de Urquiza [[uhr-KEE-zah]]</u></b> <b><u>fought Manuel Oribe [[oh-REE-beh]] and beat Juan Manuel de Rosas at (+)</u> Caseros [[kah-SEH-rohs]]. This nation was defended by the Army of the North, led by Mart\u00edn Miguel de G\u00fcemes [[GWEH-mehs]], and the Army of the (*) </b>Andes was established in this country by native son, Jos\u00e9 de San Mart\u00edn. For ten points, name this South American country with an oft-disputed Chilean border.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Argentina</u></b> (or <b><u>Argentine</u></b> Republic; or Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Argentina</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country contains the world's oldest known temple complex, whose name</u></b> <b><u>translates to \"Potbelly Hill.\" Ian Hodder currently has led the excavation of the</u></b> <b><u>\u00c7atalh\u00f6y\u00fck [[cha-tal-HOH-yook]] temple in this country. The Dede [[DEH-DEH]] is a</u></b> <b><u>spiritual leader of this country's (+)</u> Alevi faith. This country is home to the headquarters of the Sufist Mevlevi Order, and this country's most important mosques include The Blue Mosque and the (*) </b>Hagia Sophia, originally a Byzantine Church. For ten points, name this country whose major Islamic sites are found in its city of Istanbul.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Turkey</u></b> (accept <b><u>T\u00fcrkiye</u></b> Cumhuriyeti)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a religion-inspired war in this country, John Rantzau [[RAHNT-zow]] fought</u></b> <b><u>against Skipper Clement in the Count's Feud. This country lost to its neighbor in the</u></b> <b><u>Torstenson [[TOHR-sten-sun]] War and signed the treaty of (+)</u> Bromsebro [[BROOM-seb-roh]], resulting in its losing out on the Sound Dues. Christian IV of the Oldenburgs led this country in the Thirty Years' War and also founded (*) </b>Oslo during the time this country governed Norway. For ten points, name this Nordic country, mostly comprised of the Jutland peninsula.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Denmark</u></b> (accept <b><u>Denmark</u></b>-Norway)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A work by this man begins \"Universal empire is the prerogative of a writer\"</u></b> <b><u>and also states that a continent will \"startle at the unhallowed foot of an invader\"</u></b> <b><u>even when whispering a \"delusion\" like \"Satan to Eve.\" (*)</u> \"Tyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered,\" according to this man, who also writes, \"These are the times that try men's souls.\" In addition to </b><em><b>The American Crisis</b></em><b>, this man wrote a best seller and donated the proceeds to the (*) </b>American Patriots. For ten points, name this British-American author of <em>Common Sense</em>.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Paine</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b><u>Lord Rosebery privately funded a statue of this man who names a predecessor</u></b> <b><u>of the Comet Tank. This man fought David Leslie's troops at the Battle of Dunbar,</u></b> <b><u>capturing Edinburgh. At the Battle of Worcester [[WOO-ster]], this man's opponent</u></b> <b><u>had to (+)</u> hide in an oak tree. In Ireland, this man committed massacres at Basing House, Wexford, and Drogheda [[DRAW-huh-dah]] as part of a policy historian John Morrill calls \"ethnic cleansing.\" Ruling over (*) </b>Barebone's Parliament, for ten points, who was this leader of the English Commonwealth who overthrew Charles I?", "answer": "Oliver <b><u>Cromwell</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "0 [[one-point-oh]] version of this Microsoft operating system was released unsuccessfully in 1985 in an effort to compete with Apple but eventually grew to hold more than 90% of the market share.", "answer": "<b><u>Windows</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}], "bonuses": []}